[SPEAKER_02]: So, my first question was actually, you spoke about it in the last video, by, as it happens, it was related to what you mean by delighting in sensuality.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, but you did speak about it in the last video, and it was quite clear when you said that
[SPEAKER_02]: It's kind of in that attitude of anticipation, initial attitude of anticipation or background attitude of anticipation towards a particular experience or something.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, I think the question that I wanted to just to make sure that, just to clarify it is, what would be the difference between
[SPEAKER_02]: Delighting in a sensual... a thought of sensual nature and, like, engaging mentally in a... in sensuality.
[SPEAKER_02]: Is there a difference between those two things?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yes, but not like... they're not on the same level.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you were not delighting, you wouldn't be able to engage mentally.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, delight is the basis for mental engagement.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can then not engage mentally, but still delight.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you don't delight, even thinking about the sense objects, it's not centrality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there's no delight.
[SPEAKER_02]: Delighting.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, that's good.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's kind of what I thought.
[SPEAKER_02]: That the delight is more like the, yeah, the necessary condition
[SPEAKER_02]: For you to be able to engage in a thought of sensual nature, in the sense that... To welcome it, delight in it, accept what, you know, the joy that promises and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, basically, to take it for granted.
[SPEAKER_02]: And so then, even like, you know, even if you're just sitting and not even moving or doing anything, there is a difference between having, like, an attitude of
[SPEAKER_02]: Wanting to go towards something, welcoming it and delighting it, and then you can then even actively think... then there is this active thinking about something, of whatever pleasant experience that you want to have or something, that you can like actively be thinking about it, but before that, there has to be already, or prior, let's say, or kind of underlying it, there is that attitude.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, which remains there, gives you, gives the meaning, gives the context of what your mind is revolving around.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, eh... and that's why... that's why certain people would more often than not meditate with sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, suttas say the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, eh... the point is exactly that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you might not be... you might be saying no to the, eh... sensual objects.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're not engaging with them.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're refusing to think about them.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're concentrating away from them.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're getting rid of those thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, is your mind still expecting pleasure?
[SPEAKER_00]: Delight in joyful
[SPEAKER_00]: Ideas of whatever, meditation experience, and so on, and it's like, yeah, so that's, that is your intention, that is your...
[SPEAKER_00]: That is your intention, that is your context, that is your motivation.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, like, when you sit to meditate, do you sit to meditate on account, like, in a way of discerning the enduring body there, the basis, what is subjected to all these reflections?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or do you sit to meditate to constantly to evoke, to get, to produce the experience of pleasing kind?
[SPEAKER_00]: And then that's just exactly the same central principle.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's in that sense, like, even people, you know, would take on the sīla and the virtue, but in that kind of a conditional way.
[SPEAKER_00]: They would take it because, yes, they were told they need to take it in order to get this special experience of meditation and enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you're actually... if your meditation is on the level of reviewing your situation, the body, the context, the danger, the peril, the disenchantment, that it's better to give it up, then you realize, oh no, sīla and virtue is what protects me from falling deeper into this.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not conditional anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's indirectly for what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Abstaining from certain acts is what created this context of recognizing the trap, the bait, and everything else.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: That brings me to another... Yeah, that's exactly the other thing I wanted to ask about or check.
[SPEAKER_02]: Is that this...
[SPEAKER_02]: It seems that the danger in relation to sensuality or... but again, I'll come back to that in a minute, but... or even the whole domain of the senses and engagement with the senses, involvement with the senses, they... because there's...
[SPEAKER_02]: Let's say two, broadly speaking, aspects of danger that kind of appeared more or less clearly to me at different times.
[SPEAKER_02]: One of which is really in relation to the nature of this particular type of, let's say, you kind of, you can learn to recognize a particular type of, let's say, perception, or if you're in seclusion, there's nothing else, it's more like a thought, type of thought.
[SPEAKER_02]: That is, eh... it's not about, you know, initially it will be about certain types of objects, but it's more about the nature of the thought, that it's like, it contains an invitation, or a hook, or a... it requires you to... it wants you to do something, to, eh... become involved in a particular type of sense of object, or a particular type of activity or experience, in some way.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it's like... then...
[SPEAKER_02]: In relation to that, there is the danger of, like, the mind becoming disturbed, and you having to kind of hang yourself, you becoming involved, hang yourself on this particular object, or to put it like that, that you become dependent on all of this, this experience, getting something, wanting something,
[SPEAKER_02]: What will happen if I don't get it?
[SPEAKER_02]: What will happen on account of it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Becoming busy on account of it?
[SPEAKER_02]: And... and yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's the kind of type of danger of... the danger of involvement or being required to do a particular thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is there a more... even more immediate type of danger implicit?
[SPEAKER_02]: There seems like a second aspect of danger, which is really more about the fact that the... about the nature of the body as such, or the senses as such.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that nature is there, regardless of whether you engage with sensuality or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what's dangerous about it?
[SPEAKER_00]: In one case, and why it isn't dangerous in another case?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, because the reason why... Yeah, because if...
[SPEAKER_02]: If you can kind of, let's say,
[SPEAKER_02]: You see, you start to recognize that, regardless of what you do.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, let's say like this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Where does the pain come from?
[SPEAKER_00]: Suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: What's the origin of suffering?
[SPEAKER_02]: The craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: The craving, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And what is the... where does that craving exist?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it a physical thing?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's an inner attitude towards things.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's a mental.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a mental thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is the mental craving, and any craving is mental, so, is the craving a matter of choice?
[SPEAKER_00]: Can you choose to crave or choose not to crave?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, craving is something the mind does, which means suffering is something the mind causes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is the mind something you ask for?
[SPEAKER_00]: Something you can control?
[SPEAKER_00]: Something you can own?
[SPEAKER_00]: Something that obeys you?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Kind of, you're aligned with it, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: It obeys you most of the time, if the circumstances are all right.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if circumstances change, that's when you realize, you know, that mind doesn't actually want to listen to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't stop it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you suffer on account of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, you want to be free from suffering, means you need to be free from craving, which means you need to teach your mind how to stop doing it, or you need to basically understand your mind or surmount your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either way, mind does the craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how do you then stop that?
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's where the danger is.
[SPEAKER_00]: The danger of sensuality
[SPEAKER_00]: Is the danger of still... the slight doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: The little bit of sensuality means there is still a little possibility of that mind craving against you, against itself, resisting, patīgā, against anything that... and you can't control that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you cannot... you can have wishful thinking and hope that the mind won't, because, you know, you're so calm and you've been keeping precepts for so long.
[SPEAKER_00]: Fundamentally,
[SPEAKER_00]: For as long as there is a trace of sensuality, the other backside of that same trace, same phenomenon, same values of sensuality, is the value of the wild mind, which means the craving remains there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you want to see whether your mind still has that
[SPEAKER_00]: Uncontrollable threat that would turn against itself and cause immense suffering if circumstances change, if you lose health, life and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, just practice sensory strain and solitude and you'll see.
[SPEAKER_00]: When the mind doesn't get what it wants, it's going to start getting wound up.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you will recognize that that's the root of the suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I can't stop the craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can't will it away.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can't just choose it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what I can do is tame the mind, so it becomes unable to turn against itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's where you recognize the true danger of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, giving in to sensual desire, even on the mental level, valuing it, means allowing mind to remain wild to that extent.
[SPEAKER_00]: And sooner or later, that will bite you back.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not a... what I'm trying to say, it's not a delayed danger.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the other side of the same coin.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's that.
[SPEAKER_00]: When danger becomes apparent, means this, as we said, this anticipation, this delight, literally, this thing, while it is present, the background of it, is mind eating itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: The possibility of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Won't do it there, but the fact is you're allowing it, and if you go that way, to that extent, you gave your own mind room to turn against itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then it will.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sooner or later it will.
[SPEAKER_00]: As long as you don't abandon that attitude and that anticipation, and you don't see thoroughly the the peril of giving in to that direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Once you do, and as the Buddha said, you drive up from sensuality internally, then the mind, the animal, will be completely tamed.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will forget how to turn against itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's where you recognize that, okay, so now suffering cannot arise.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if the circumstances are completely falling apart around me, everything disintegrating, what cannot happen is mind turn against itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you tamed it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you won't tame it for as long as there is... as long as you allow it to eat the bait, or welcome the bait, or delight in the bait, or think about the bait.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the bait you refer to is basically prospect of pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Value of pleasure, delight in pleasure, prospect of pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the bait is also... like, it's not... prospect of pleasure can show the bait, but it also... simply... kind of not seeing the danger enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's also what the bait is.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's all it means.
[SPEAKER_00]: You value pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Either not recognizing the bait, in a way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Seeing the danger is how you basically stop valuing the pleasure and recognize the bait.
[SPEAKER_00]: The bait is the bait.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, the bait is the bait.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not... what I'm trying to say, it's not like that you don't need to actively seek out and then, oh, I don't actively seek out, thus I'm free from bait.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you now, by... okay, you don't actively seek out, but do you now see the danger if you were to seek out?
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you don't see the danger, to that extent, yeah, you still don't see the bait.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't see the bait, if you don't see the danger.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when the bait, or when this prospect is seen as the bait, as something that will hook me, then the light decreases.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: When the prospect of that
[SPEAKER_00]: Anticipation is seeing this thing is what makes mind bite itself.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what I meant.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's when you just adopt it.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's nothing, no pleasure in the world, there's no way to accept it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it's not the... it's that, like, thing...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's nothing to do with the thing you want.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's nothing.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's that, like...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's what... giving in to that, or maintaining that, or not seeing the danger of that,
[SPEAKER_00]: And perpetuates, enables the mind, and perpetuates that enabling of mind to bite itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: When things change, when you're paired with what you don't want, separated from what you want, the, you know, the five codes of sensual pleasures and so on,
[SPEAKER_00]: And you know that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know that you will not be able to stop it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can just hope and ignore it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But factually, if there is a room for a mind to bite itself, it will.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you allowed it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the danger.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yes, you can involve the future peril and dissatisfaction, sure, to reign it in.
[SPEAKER_00]: But fundamentally, accepting this means mind biting itself.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, that's... that's exactly what I... what I meant.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like that... that's... that's so nice to...
[SPEAKER_02]: The danger is in that any kind of... That's what you just said, so I don't need to repeat it.
[SPEAKER_02]: That is the danger.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's nothing to do with what will happen in the future or what could happen in the future or whatever.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, that's like, oh, you could... it could not happen, or it could be fine, whatever.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, that's... it's... it's just that fact of being hooked, one... of, like, having this... yeah, having a hook, having a push, having a... having any kind of craving is in itself to be not desired, to be not welcomed, because it's the way
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like the gateway to hell, really.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's this great mass of suffering, as the Buddha described.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's the gateway to hell.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's because of that, the great mass of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the great mass of suffering is always on account of the same cause.
[SPEAKER_00]: The same core.
[SPEAKER_00]: Presence of craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything else is second to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And as we described, presence of craving, craving, full stop, is something that the mind that hasn't been tame will do.
[SPEAKER_00]: We're faced with agreeable, disagreeable or neutral.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, the great mass of suffering remains something that you are under.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you are liable to it, you will be subjected to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, if the danger of sensuality has been understood, I... Oh, okay, so...
[SPEAKER_00]: Without... if I stop, if I don't give in to this, if I don't welcome this, because now I see, if I do, this is the result.
[SPEAKER_00]: The result is mind remaining able to eat itself, if it wants to, in a split second.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not like, you know, it will not be a long process.
[SPEAKER_00]: All you need to do is face with something you don't want to face with,
[SPEAKER_00]: And all the dread and pain and everything will be instantaneously there, because the mind will just try to turn away from it, to resist it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, again, you let it... you gave it room to do so.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why it's hard to see, because, you know, room to do so, doesn't mean the mind is doing it all the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you then forget that the mind can still do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It can still turn against itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: It can still want to deny its own existence out of pain and aversion and hatred and ill will and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But because it's not doing that all the time, you sort of forget that there is room for it to still turn around and sink its teeth.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the danger.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that was something, eh... that was another point that's... that's why, like, it's not, eh...
[SPEAKER_02]: Being like... having a kind of a sense of safety or something, is not about just currently not feeling any sort of pressure of the sensual kind, because you can
[SPEAKER_02]: You have that, even for quite a long time, for example.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: But as soon as something comes up, something arises, then, if at that moment, then, you will be going in that direction, not able to see the problem in it, not recognizing it for what it is, then, there is no safety, really, at all.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what is the safety then?
[SPEAKER_00]: The true safety?
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, the safety is when you know where the danger is, then, you
[SPEAKER_02]: know that no matter when it will...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you know now that the danger is in mind being able to turn against itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, where is then the safety?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, if you see the danger of that, then the
[SPEAKER_02]: But if the mind is able to turn itself against itself, what makes the mind being able to turn itself against itself, that's something that you are responsible for, that you can choose to not do.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you recognize the danger of doing that which makes the mind able to turn against itself, then you can not do that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, eventually, the mind will cease to be able to turn against itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, that's true safety.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: Craving cannot arise.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, so you said that now, like, recognizing where the danger is, is the necessary condition for safety.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, is there... but is there... yeah, is there also a sense that the kind of...
[SPEAKER_02]: I think it's something slightly different.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, let's say, from the perspective of...
[SPEAKER_02]: Not being... not having any safety, there's... if you're still like in the domain of sensuality and kind of involved in it, I kind of don't see how it's possible, in a way, to see the danger in it.
[SPEAKER_02]: It kind of requires at least, say, maybe not the complete sense of safety, but at least
[SPEAKER_02]: Pretty complete seclusion from that domain, in order to then have the perspective of... That's why sensory strength and guarding of the sense doors is a prerequisite that's normally optional.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It needs to be your lifestyle, your mode of being.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: In itself, you will still not see.
[SPEAKER_00]: Where the danger is and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But for sure, if you're not withdrawn, then you remove even possibility of seeing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like we said before, like lighting the fire.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the Buddha said, you know, the sticks are in the water, wet.
[SPEAKER_00]: You take them out of the water first.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, if you try to light the fire with sticks in the water, that's just not going to work.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you take them out, but they're still wet.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, although, yes, they are out of water,
[SPEAKER_00]: They're still wet, so they still won't light the fire.
[SPEAKER_00]: But now, at least, there is a possibility of them drying, if you don't put them back in the water.
[SPEAKER_00]: And once they're dry, thoroughly, then you can light the fire.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: The mind is first physically withdrawn from sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Through your own behavior, you withdraw it by not giving in to this behavior, because you recognize on it.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, out of faith, to a degree, but at the same time, you do recognize, I've been going down the direction of the senses my whole life, and look, I want to practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: I want to be free from suffering, because this is what it resulted in.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, you found the Buddha's teaching, you have a degree of faith, you start applying it, and you can even intellectually make sense that
[SPEAKER_00]: Actually, it's better if I'm out of the water, even if I don't necessarily see the immediate imminent danger, the direct insight into freedom from sensuality and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, at least I have a possibility to do so if I stay out of the water.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And like that...
[SPEAKER_00]: But in and of itself, that's not a goal.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: The goal is to light a fire and you don't forget that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And again, just to clarify slightly further, that
[SPEAKER_02]: Being out of the water, because this could maybe be understood in different ways, as far as I can see, it really has to become quite a complete seclusion, as in, it wouldn't really be
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, yeah, you can be kind of more or less restrained in keeping the virtue, but if you are still, like, busy doing various things and kind of distracting yourself in any way, really,
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you kind of can't really even see this... which type of... Yeah, but that's like, you know, seeing the danger in the slightest fault does not mean seeing the danger in the slightest fault of the letter and the semantics of the rule.
[SPEAKER_00]: means the danger of the slightest fault, in terms of, okay, so yes, I'm not breaking this...
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm not giving in to desire by body, but to this coarse extent, but am I still looking forward to and eating things that are allowable, as we said before.
[SPEAKER_00]: Also, I must stop... No, you must stop eating with that desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't stop eating.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if a person never recognizes that that's where the true danger and fault is, and still remain on the level of, you know, oh, I studied all the dictionary and I got the definition of the rule, and this is what objectively means, and a fault of that, in regard to that interpretation, is what I deem a fault, so I just need to fix the circumstances and make everybody else obey it, that's not seeing the fault.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not allowing, basically,
[SPEAKER_00]: Vinaya and sense restraint to make you practice on the level of the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is just using it to protect yourself through that magical belief that that's where the purity is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in order to abandon Sīla Bhāgavatam, you need to realize where the fault is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's not in the letter.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not in the in the definition.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's in, like, why am I doing this?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you find something that's not against the rules.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that still doesn't absolve you from needing to know and feel the weight of why you're doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, coffee is allowable to have in the afternoon.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I can have sugar.
[SPEAKER_00]: But why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why am I doing this?
[SPEAKER_00]: Where is this rooted?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah, it's been, you know, it's been traditionally often touched, you know, with a bowing, triple bowing on a tray.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's just the purest offering I can imagine in that external form sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, yeah, but that's... that's irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_00]: The fault is not in how it was done and presented.
[SPEAKER_00]: The fault is, why am I doing this?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do I need it?
[SPEAKER_00]: What for?
[SPEAKER_00]: Where is it suited?
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, same would come to exactly like, oh, yeah, so, you know, we are allowed to to work and do these things and like, but, yeah, but why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, what I was like, it's even stu... you know, you can't be alone.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it necessary?
[SPEAKER_00]: Where is it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's the same study.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's exactly the same study.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why am I reading the suttas?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: These duties that you perceive are kind of self-evident and objectively valid, that's not where the validity is determined.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's determined by your intentions and the reasons why you do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yes, obvious things out of greed, aversion, delusion, eight precepts, basically, are not to be broken.
[SPEAKER_00]: But now all the other implementation doesn't mean you can dismiss them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Quite the opposite.
[SPEAKER_00]: Means you need to take more of them, just on the right level.
[SPEAKER_00]: Less specifically, but more.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're taking responsibility for where the actual fault is.
[SPEAKER_00]: The mind of desire, mind of aversion, and mind of distraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if we judge what needs to be done on the basis of authority, of the texts, which is, again, a contradiction in terms, like, you will always have your interpretation of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no such thing as objective meaning of the text.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's what it means to you and to us.
[SPEAKER_00]: And vast majority of people might agree upon the meaning, but every single one of them is individually subjectively responsible for that meaning.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the weight of the tradition, the authority and so on, that's not... that's not where these things are.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you never abandon that, out of fear of doubt and so on, well, you'll never allow your mind to recognize where the true fault is and thus uproot it, out of fear and doubt.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's really like...
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to get out of the water for the sake of drying the sticks, not for the sake of drying underwater and then just, you know, defining what the water was and how you dry and, you know, what you must, what you can, what you cannot do.
[SPEAKER_00]: From the point of view of desire, you can't do anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not out of water.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's...
[SPEAKER_00]: If the light in the fire is your goal.
[SPEAKER_00]: If not, you know, if just living in a spiritual community that agrees upon certain terms and interpretations is your goal, then fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's not what we're talking about.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, just to come back to this, the degree of, let's say, the degree of seclusion,
[SPEAKER_02]: And it's...
[SPEAKER_02]: I think in the suttas, it's sometimes even says like, he goes into physical seclusion and mental seclusion, or physical withdrawal and mentally secluded, or mentally withdrawn.
[SPEAKER_02]: Can you be mentally withdrawn if you're not physically withdrawn?
[SPEAKER_02]: No, you cannot.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, there's the physical sense of withdrawal, but even...
[SPEAKER_02]: It needs more than, like, physically being secluded, let's say, in a secluded environment, or just being restrained.
[SPEAKER_02]: There is necessity for mental... to be mentally withdrawn from even mentally engaging in unwholesome things, for which you need to be able to already see how you are mentally engaging with unwholesome things.
[SPEAKER_02]: In order to then be able to see the danger in doing so, in order to then kind of have any kind of sense of safety.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in other words, you need to basically want to light the fire.
[SPEAKER_00]: And in order to do so, you need to abandon things, external things, avoidance of responsibilities,
[SPEAKER_00]: External authorities, external agreements, as the measure of your safety, purity, practice in defining what you need to do, you need to abandon your perceived sense of duty.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you need to abandon sīla-bhāt-parmasa, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's used, you know, these fetters and all these random things, they serve a purpose.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're fettered, willingly, by them, because they protect you from that which is very displeasing.
[SPEAKER_00]: The weight of responsibility, the weight of interpretation, the weight of choices, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, which way you have a choice to make?
[SPEAKER_00]: You can remain sheltered, covering things up, and if you want to uncover it, then you have to unshelter it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That to me, like, the true safety comes from mind being unable to turn against itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: But in order to arrive there, you need to stop covering up the fact that the mind can turn against itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, but I'm fine, you know, I keep the precepts and I'm pure and I'm devotional and stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, yeah, but that's... that is all just conditional.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, that's nice in a worldly sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then you need to start asking yourself, why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why am I doing this?
[SPEAKER_00]: If I took, oh no, I agree with this, with this authority, with this traditional interpretation or whatever else, the way what we should do, fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you still need to know why and take responsibility for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's never on them.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's never on others.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's never on the, as I said, on the on the external world.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you say, yeah, I'll agree to what you already agreed, that still doesn't absolve me from needing to know why I'm doing that and think for myself and take responsibility for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But often, that's exactly why it's done.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, I will go with majority, with the tradition, with the established ways, so I don't have to think for myself.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you are thinking for yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, you're just lying to yourself about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because how would you choose to go with the tradition, with the established ways, unless you thought about it, and obviously felt some safety on account of it, and gave in to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And now you're just saying, I don't know, I just go with what others say.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you do need to take responsibility for it, and then it ceases to be on that level.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you realize it's all... it is all interpretation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Eight precepts are interpretation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, yeah, you know, you can bend it this way, bend it that way, sure, but fundamentally you realize, okay, you could extrapolate the principle of greed, aversion, delusion, sensual desire, ill-will, carelessness, distraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is what needs to be restrained.
[SPEAKER_00]: How we define it, and can I touch this, and if it's touch, can I do this, and well, you know, if I said it, okay, you can go into these details if it's helpful, but not for the sake of deriving safety from the definition that you read in a book or a senior monk told you.
[SPEAKER_00]: But simply from knowing more how to recognize the root of the problem in your mind, so that the greed, aversion, delusion doesn't hide from you, or that you don't feel absorbed from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So when I recognize that there is nothing I... nothing at all I have to do, or nothing at all that I can do, that can absolve me from taking responsibility for whatever I choose to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And also, furthermore, on a more immediate level, it will be
[SPEAKER_00]: If you abandon Sīlavāda Paramārtha, it would be like, oh, I don't need to do anything in order to be safe.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's unsafe.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the relief of abandoning the factors, it's factual.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not intellectual.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's exactly on that level.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, it is a burden.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having to define, having to follow, having to update, having to comply, having to do, having to perform.
[SPEAKER_00]: All of that is a factual burden.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't see the burden in aspect, because you emphasize the sheltering aspect.
[SPEAKER_00]: Once you stop shelt... emphasizing that aspect, you can actually, eventually, if you go in the right direction, abandon the burden of it and it is... No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: Quite the opposite.
[SPEAKER_00]: If I don't engage that way, I am...
[SPEAKER_00]: I remain safe.
[SPEAKER_00]: I remain unexposed.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in a way, it's on account of the loss of perspective?
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't understand.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like you say that you...
[SPEAKER_01]: You pay more attention, in a way, to the sheltering aspect, but not to how it affects you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, I wouldn't say it's on account of loss of perspective, because you never had the perspective.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you start by not having perspective.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's on account of the lack of perspective.
[SPEAKER_00]: Loss would imply you sort of had it and then you lost it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, no, you start already affected.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, and that's...
[SPEAKER_02]: It's why... it's like... in a way that, like, Sīla Bhātta Paramahāsa, for example, kind of covers up.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what it does.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what its purpose is, really, is to make something appear comfortable, or feel comfortable, that isn't comfortable, and that shouldn't be comfortable, and as in that... What do you mean?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because the avoiding responsibility for things through having things, duties and others depending on other things to tell you, it kind of makes this... Yeah, makes it comfortable.
[SPEAKER_00]: I see what you mean, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Makes it doable, but actually nothing is changed on a fundamental level.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no fire, you're not closer to light in the fire.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you shouldn't be comfortable.
[SPEAKER_00]: You should recognize that there is still plenty of room for mind to turn against itself in many different ways.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, yeah, you will feel absolved from needing to deal with it because, you know, abide under the the collective responsibility of majority that we all contributed and all partake and I'm safe.
[SPEAKER_00]: Safety of the group.
[SPEAKER_00]: Safety of the tribe.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's kind of gone off in a different... slightly different direction.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now, I wanted to come back to the... if it's okay, we're kind of going in different directions, but it's...
[SPEAKER_02]: I wanted to come back to the hindrances, because...
[SPEAKER_02]: Another question I had, like, I was... because I often...
[SPEAKER_02]: I realized, basically, that often I would... sometimes it's not that clear to me, even, what exactly is meant by, say, sensual thought, or like a... yeah, because sometimes...
[SPEAKER_02]: I often, I'm kind of, I think of it in terms of not necessarily defined by particular, yeah, particular objects or having even something necessarily being agreeable in a way.
[SPEAKER_02]: What I realized that sometimes things that I was thinking of as like, yeah, sensuality, because it really pertains to like engaging in a some kind of experience or feeling like the need to do something really.
[SPEAKER_02]: But
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not really... it would kind of come down to...
[SPEAKER_02]: I realize, oh, that's more like doubt, or that's more like, kind of, another one of the hindrances, or it's more like the same, kind of, the same... Yeah, the thread of hindrances.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're bound together.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it can be on the level of specific sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touch, or, like, the overall agreeability of the... of, you know, the experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it does always imply that that sense of
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why in the Sutta, the Buddha talks about perfect celibacy.
[SPEAKER_00]: It starts by, yeah, not having sexual intercourse.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, he was talking to monks.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, not having sexual intercourse with women.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're not touching them.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're not allowing to be touched.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're not talking to them.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're not listening to them talk.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're not looking at them.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're not thinking about them.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're not wishing about having any rebirths.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it was the extension of the same principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, okay, I might have abandoned any kind of physical kāna, all these pleasures that would be binding me here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, but I still hope that this, I will find somewhere else here, some new here, where it will be nice and pleasant and safe for me, where pleasures will be accessible.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in other words, are you still valuing
[SPEAKER_00]: A situation external to your state of mind here and now, for pleasure, for safety, there is a thread of centrality, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's when, like, if... same, like, whether it's meditation or any other, if you're expecting this thing to come on the level of just this external experience that just happened internally now and everything else, it's the... it's the same principle, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you might, sorry, like, you know, you can't, you cannot necessarily tell your mind to immediately stop thinking about those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can certainly not lose perspective or learn how to not lose perspective on account of having those thoughts present.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, and the thing this... And what would be the perspective, by the way?
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's say, how would you not lose a perspective on a spectrum of sexual intercourse with a, you know, whoever I'm attracted to?
[SPEAKER_00]: Up to the level of wishing heavenly rebirths and safety of heavens, what is the... how would you maintain perspective at any part of that spectrum, any thought, wherever it is?
[SPEAKER_00]: What would maintain the perspective of the entire thing, of the entire domain?
[SPEAKER_02]: What would maintain the perspective of the... What would make you not lose perspective?
[SPEAKER_02]: Whether it's a coarse, carnal, sensual desire, or heavenly... Well, it's to be recognizing that danger of that whole... that you've said.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the same danger.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, it's the same danger, whether it's...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yes, Heavens, you know, it's better, actually.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you have a desire towards Heavens, then have a desire towards carnal pleasures here and now, which are far worse, with far worse consequences.
[SPEAKER_00]: Unintended consequences.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, fundamentally, if you want to be free from it all, fundamentally, if you don't want to leave the slightest room for your mind to turn against itself,
[SPEAKER_00]: Even in hundred millions years of time in the future, it's... see the same danger.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then there will be no room for mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then the craving will truly be abandoned.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that... yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if the danger is seen there, then it really doesn't matter at all whether... like there is no kind of even asking, oh, but it's little, or it's big, or it's small, or whatever, like whatever way, whatever domain.
[SPEAKER_02]: In whatever shape, whatever, it's not about.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like... And the thing is, as well... And that's what Guru was describing.
[SPEAKER_00]: The suttas, you know, we talk about aggregates and I see danger in them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Similarly, we said it doesn't matter whether it's past, future, present, big, small, personal, impersonal, foreign, familiar, nice, light, heavy.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter the property of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: The danger is seen the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not mine, not to be welcomed, not to be delighted in.
[SPEAKER_00]: And see that long enough, and the mind will calm down.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, the mind will become unable to turn against itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: Cannot be done anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's like the description of the true freedom, the true safety.
[SPEAKER_00]: It cannot be reverted back, like a stone split into leaves, sort of dried up.
[SPEAKER_00]: It cannot now go back.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it has been completely dry.
[SPEAKER_00]: Fire has been lit.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sticks were burned.
[SPEAKER_00]: Gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: There are no more sticks to be wet.
[SPEAKER_01]: What leads... what is dangerous, so to say.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like the bait.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: The prospect of, oh, let me get this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, let me have it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's my safety.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's my safety.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because I enjoy the comfort, the familiarity, the friendliness of the taste that the bait has.
[SPEAKER_00]: And as we said last time, it's not... it does not start when I act.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: It starts when I...
[SPEAKER_00]: Already.
[SPEAKER_00]: With the light, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're already... you're already not seeing it as dangerous.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where it starts.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's exactly what the
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, why, that's even the danger is in the delight towards it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's the gratification, that's the danger, it's on that level.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's all on that, in that same kernel.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the same phenomenon, just different aspects of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why we keep it as the same thing, in a way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you were to not act out of the delight long enough,
[SPEAKER_00]: And get to discern the background, not ignore it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You would see that the background of it is the bait.
[SPEAKER_00]: The delight is the bait.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: The bait is the danger.
[SPEAKER_02]: The delight is the danger.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, that's really... And all the future consequences, it's all because of this.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is the framework.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is the necessary basis.
[SPEAKER_00]: This will be there if those consequences are to experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, and yeah, and it's... and like from the perspective of seeing that, then like the slightest, you know,
[SPEAKER_02]: prospect of, you know, going towards that, going in that direction, is very unpleasant, actually, or it would be very unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like, it's almost like, you know, you're out of prison,
[SPEAKER_02]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: And now, you see, like, the prison guard is going, oh, come back in here.
[SPEAKER_02]: I have some very nice, I don't know, cake.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, but the fear would be on the level of, oh, this crazy mind might forget and go back.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you know you wouldn't, but if the mind is still not tamed, if it still has room to move, you realize that's the danger.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that was the simile of the, was it, the charcoal pit.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Man initially goes willingly there and burns himself with the embers because he perceives it pleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, he gets cured.
[SPEAKER_00]: He doesn't have a need for that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if somebody were to pick him up and carry him there, wouldn't he kick and scream and want to be everywhere else except there?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it's like, yeah, you're... and you really can see, like, God,
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, why would anybody want to, like, actually go in that direction when...
[SPEAKER_02]: But you do.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what I kind of meant.
[SPEAKER_02]: In a way, for that, you do already need the perspective of, like, some kind of safety.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't have that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Kind of perspective from already being in it and seeing that as the safety.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it's gonna have like, you know, seeing that principle will be done on different levels, like different layers.
[SPEAKER_00]: You'll be feeling it more and more.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, yeah, it will be the same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: But up until to the point, you realize that if I were to die this next second,
[SPEAKER_00]: Will my mind have immersion towards that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Will it try to sort of, you know, resist it, fight it, deal with it, avoid it, close its eyes, look away?
[SPEAKER_00]: If so, or if I'm not sure, means there is still room for it to move.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: To bite itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that cannot... should not be allowed if I want to be truly free, secured from bondage.